so unlike the principles in this book
The intelligent investor by Benjamin
Graham we're not going to be talking
about the value investing that is most
famously employed by Warren Buffett
today instead we're going to be talking
about how most analysts would go about
comparing different management funds and
looking at the returns and looking at a
risk weighted metric of those returns so
what most analysts might do is jump
straight to the sharp ratio now this is
what we want to talk about today what
are the biggest assumptions behind this
point Value Estimate of the sharp ratio
and what are the downfalls so let's jump
into it for the purpose of this video
we're just going to focus on a very
specific example if I have a number of
portfolios that I need to choose between
why should I not be just jumping
straight to the sharp ratio well let's
look at the example where we have only
12 portfolio managers that we're trying
to assess here I'm just assigning their
mean standard deviations in this skew in
their portfolio distributions randomly
now I'm also randomly assigning in the
number of years that these portfolios
have been in existence for and therefore
how many years worth of data we have to
actually judge our analysis from this is
important because obviously for some
portfolios they've only started last
year or some have been in existence for
30 years so this impacts our assessment
so let's take a quick look at our
histogram that I've just plotted I've
taking um the distributions with skew
standard deviations mean and I'm just
simulating what it would look like for a
number of years so this is just one
outcome so here's a comparison of our
portfolio managers returns over the last
say 23 years for manager one is manager
zero manager 1 has 7even years manager 2
28 years of portfolio returns and this
is the data that we get presented with
we get one actual real life Iz ation
over a number of years of what that
portfolio fund has done so this is real
world data quote unquote real world data
that we've just simulated based on the
true distributions So based on this real
world data from all our managers that
have been operating for a different
number of years how can we deduce what
their true strategy sharp ratio is well
you might go Jonathan that's really easy
to come up with what we can do is we can
use the central limit theorem assume the
central limit theorem and use it to
infer the sharp ratios now most people
might not know that they're assuming the
central limit theorum and this is half
of the problem so the aim is we'd like
to compare the sharp ratio between a
number of different investment managers
how do we do it well essentially here's
the estimate of the sharp ratio we have
the expectation of our returns minus the
risk flee rate and then that's
normalized by our volatility of the
asset that we're analyzing
so therefore we can just do the simple
thing which is take the means and the
standard deviations assume a risk-free
rate of 4% before you go crazy in the
comments let's just remember that this
video is supposed to last the trajectory
of time so risk-free rate we just
assuming to be 4% we're looking and
considering this as a opportunity cost
or as a hurdle rate so therefore we're
calculating our sharp ratios for each of
the managers using our mean and standard
deviation as per this formula so now we
get our data frame and we can see here
we've got the mean standard deviation
and the sharp ratio and here we've just
ordered it based on the sharp ratio now
remember that we are taking into
consideration that risk-free rate so
that's why we've got more negatives here
than the mean have negatives here so if
we just list them from least to best
what you would say is probably oh let's
just invest all our money with this
portfolio manager but is that the right
thing to do well the problem is that
this is just one value and currently I
have no idea about my uncertainty in
that estimate so let's try and dig a
little bit deeper and understand more
about what we're assuming when we just
blindly take this formula and uh and
compute the mean and the standard
deviations in order to compute a one
value sharp ratio so the biggest
assumption and the most important one
we're estimating is using the maximum
likelihood estimation from the normal
distribution so this assumes the
property of the central limit theorem
that as our data goes to Infinity we
then get a normal distribution so we're
going to explain how that works now so
what is the central limit theorem well
essentially the central limit theorem if
you take any sum of ROM variables that
are independently and identically
distributed so IID with a finite
variance regardless of the distribution
as the number of random
variables you summing approaches
Infinity the scaled summation so
normalized for the mean drift and the
variance as you start adding up these
variables converges to the normal
distribution so my favorite video that
explains this better than anyone else
could is on the three blue one brown uh
YouTube channel and I recommend giving
it a watch essentially they've got a
really nice animation there where
they show as you start adding up for an
uneven die as you start adding up these
values and running the experiment again
and again and again again the histogram
starts uh converging towards a normal
distribution I think it's a fascinating
animation go watch the video so let's
use an example that actually cements
this principle in our head of the
central limit theorem so we have one
investment manager now and we're just
going to Define his actual returns
distribution so let's say that his
actual distribution with the team that
he's got and the strategies that he has
year after year it's invariant it
doesn't change that would be a long uh
long ask but let's say that it didn't
change so it's time invariant we have a
mean of 8% a standard deviation of 15%
and minus one as a skew now let's just
sample just for the sake of
visualization of the distribution 1
million points from this distribution
and I'm just returning here the
distribution as you can see from this
distribution we have um quite a large
skew to the right hand side with that
really fat tail to the left hand side
with that downside risk present so in in
order to understand how this would look
if we invested with this portfolio
management um year after year let's run
a regular Monte Caro experiment so a
picture that I'm 25 years old and I
would like to invest my money for the
next 25e period so I want to be able to
take my money out when I'm 50 years old
let's say that we choose this portfolio
manager with this
distribution so we want to investigate
the portfolio characteristics why now
specifically we would like to say
something about the expectation of what
we could expect our portfolio returns to
be in 25 years so here by using mon
Carlo we can essentially get the sample
distribution of the mean which is
essentially just the average of all
these simulation that we're about to run
now we're interested in seeing something
about these um the mean and the variance
and because of this we can rely on the
central limit theorem which essentially
says that once um we take this sample
mean over a large period of time periods
as n goes to Infinity this then
converges in distribution to the normal
distribution centered around the mean
and then this scaled variance metric
so we have an empirical variance which
is estimated like this and we have a
standard error and the error is around
the fact that we're only taking um an
average of randomly generated samples
when we're doing monteo simulation so
therefore the calculation is itself
random and therefore the measure that
exists around this error is a standard
um error and it's denoted by um this
equation here so we take the standard
deviation that we get from our actual
simulations and then essentially we
divide that and normalize it by the
square root of the number of simulations
so how do we do that let's define the
holding period in Python we' got 25
years number of theoretical simulations
10,000 so we're going to sample from our
distribution of our returns from our
manager and we're going to actually
check something we're going to check for
the cases where the returns were less
than minus one so AKA we actually lost
all our money in one year because of
this aggressive leftand side tail with
our portfolio manager and lo and behold
this actually happened three times but
it was three times out of
10,000 random uh simulations so picture
uh 10,000 people um all all in
consecutive things and we had a
portfolio manager with the exact same
distribution only three times out of
those 10,000 did someone lose all that
money um in one year which would have
been a shame you wouldn't make it to the
end of your retirement at 50,000 with
anything so this happens because the max
return in a single year was 37 but the
minimum single uh return in a single
year was minus uh 113 which obviously
can't happen means your account drained
to zero now for all those samples where
we actually had a continuation and we
made it to the end of the holding period
let's take the accumulation the
summation over those paths so we're
going to take the log returns because we
can sum the log returns to actually get
the total returns over the 25 years
we've made a video on that before please
check our Channel out so the plot of
final histogram of the returns at 50
years of age are like here so what we've
got we've got the Monte Carlo mean
estimate is
164% uh returns over 25e period and our
standard error is just 2% and that's to
the 95
percentile so we're using standard error
and we're using using the critical value
of
1.96 because that's what the T the uh
critical values are for the standard
normal distribution for the 95 perenti
now we have a video on our channel that
goes more into Monty Carlo simulations
and to understand this a little bit more
I recommend checking out one of those
videos now for the sole purpose here we
can see that this is not one number so
if we had just used the sharp ratio as
per our data frame that we' ordered on
before and then we used that and we
assumed that that value was going to
hold true over our investment period of
25 years then we would have ended up
with one number and we would have said
hey look everything's good with positive
but look here we've used a Monte Carlo
simulation and we've understood that
there is risk that at the end of 25
years I might be the person that's here
in the bar chart and have lost my money
completely compared to I might also be
very very lucky I might be the person
who's benefited completely and it's
important to remember that this is with
the true distribution of a manager who
has the exact same
distribution so this is all the possible
outcomes that could happen if I'm
investing in the One
Fund now let's understand what happens
if we change the holding time so let's
consider what happens if we reduce our
holding time from 25 years down to 1
year 2 years 5 years 10 years and then
we're going to make a ridiculous claim
where we actually go up to a thous uh
10,000 years so obviously this is a bit
ridiculous example but it's just showing
you the power of the central limit
theorem so if all these simulations came
from the portfolio manager with those
returns that we saw before what would
that look like as you can see by looking
at the results from the one year the 2E
the 5e we've got this really long
leftand tail right with this skew to the
right side distribution now this is
looking very similar to the actual true
distribution of the portfolio return and
this is no coincidence so essentially
what we're doing is we've realized one
year
here what is our portfolio in the one
year and what's the outcome and this
should nearly exactly follow the
distribution of the portfolio manager in
the second year we're realizing a a year
so getting a certain percentage return
and then we're simulating again and
adding that number and we're doing that
again and again and again up to 10,000
years and what you can see at the 10,000
years we're very very likely to have our
8% return which is around the mem and
then we're very very confident about
that you can see how the standard error
around this Monte Carlo simulation
actually is really really insignificant
so if we could live for 10,000 years
with this portfolio manager and he
didn't change his strategy year on year
on year we would be very likely to get
our 8% return if we only hold for one
year we have a huge variance in our
likely outcomes all the way down from
losing our money completely um through
to getting an outrageous return and as
you increase the years this distribution
gets closer and closer to the normal
distribution so this is is just one of
the best examples that I can show you of
what is the central limit theorum and
what are we assuming when we do it in
finance for our
returns now in the real world we can't
live for 10,000 uh lives over over that
25 times years so you might be the guy
that in the one-ear scenario you're all
the way down here or you might be the
person down here you don't get to choose
that part you also can't live for a
th000 10,000 years which is is a bit sad
but we can't assume that we're going to
get 8% returns with this level of
accuracy unfortunately or fortunately we
only end up living one life and
therefore we end up as one of these
histogram bars at a particular point in
the future therefore given the data we
have right now on the fund what
inference can we make about the returns
and one of the options that's available
to us and what most people assume and
jump to immediately is using the maximum
likelihood estimator and they trust in
the central limit theorem even if the
fund's only been around for 2 years and
has limited data I've put something
together here about the maximum
likelihood estimator function you don't
need to read it all um I'll just briefly
explain it here essentially what you're
trying to do we're assuming a
distribution and we're getting data and
we want to given the observed data find
what the parameters of that distribution
are that yield the highest joint
probability
for that data set so we're assuming the
normal distribution here and we're
asking what's the mean and standard
deviation that would give me the highest
joint probability of observing the data
that I've got now um to do that you need
the probability density function here's
the one for the normal distribution and
then you take the joint probability
function of observing that data so for
my likelihood parameters I've got my mu
and my uh variance term there but what
is the joint probability of my observed
data um as a function of these
statistical parameters and then using
this data essentially we can do a
maximization function and we don't do it
directly on the likelihood function
because this can lead to arithm
underflow problem which is just we're
trying to hold in memory on the computer
really small numbers instead this is
done indirectly on the log of the
likelihood function so it's just simply
a maximization problem
trying to um assign what values would be
most likely to be observed in the joint
probability distribution given this data
here really at the end of the day for
the normal distribution someone's done
the hard job for you they've gone
through the math and they've come up
with these uh factors here so our best
estimate given the data is um the mean
the estimate mean is essentially the
average of the returns and the biased uh
estimator here here of variance is equal
to the standard deviation the biased
estimator so it's important assumption
here is that all samples of this
distribution are assumed to be IID and
come from the underlying normal
distribution which we've already
established as an okay assumption as we
have data that's going to
Infinity so let's now use use those
formulas and do what we did right at the
top we've got 25 years
um that we're holding for we've got our
true distribution of our uh Investment
Portfolio manager and now I want to plot
only one lifetime I'm only going to live
from 25 hopefully make it to 50 once so
what was my results I've run that
simulation I've lived once for 25 years
and at the end of the day my Sharp ratio
was .57 but our actual me was is
estimated via that process of 9% with a
standard deviation standard error of 16
um
16% so we it's very very hard if we're
actually receiving data from a uh random
variable process and trying to actually
understand what the distribution of
returns are especially with low number
of time periods so essentially what
we've realized though is that by doing
this uh this mle estimation and assuming
the normal distribution we only ever end
up with one point estimate of the data
our sharp ratio we don't understand the
uncertainty around this number so
although we might get estimates back
like the standard error around our um
mean estimate of the distribution we
don't understand what our worst case
scenario is or our best case scenario
with this single point value of the
sharp ratio so in following videos we're
going to talk about this more and then
how we can actually uh use different
principles use different modeling to
actually get a better estimate and a
better understanding of the risks
involved when we're actually trying to
assume what the distributions are of
portfolio management returns so thank
you very much for listening I've put all
the code and this into a article in
medium so please check it down in the
description below for a link to that
until next time YouTube see you
later
[Music]